<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian liberty not to be abused, or, Antient and primitive truth correcting some modern, or new abuses, of that which is so much pleaded for, and so little understood, viz. Christian liberty in a sermon preached in the church of Bridport within the county of Dorset, on Sunday the forenoon, being November 3. 1672 ... / by Rich. Luce ...</title>
            <author>Luce, Richard, Presbyter of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3423A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11964205</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11964205</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51655</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49413)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51655)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 817:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian liberty not to be abused, or, Antient and primitive truth correcting some modern, or new abuses, of that which is so much pleaded for, and so little understood, viz. Christian liberty in a sermon preached in the church of Bridport within the county of Dorset, on Sunday the forenoon, being November 3. 1672 ... / by Rich. Luce ...</title>
                  <author>Luce, Richard, Presbyter of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rowland Reynolds ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, II, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Liberty --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty --  Religious aspects --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51655:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51655:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTIAN LIBERTY Not to be ABUSED: OR, Antient and Primitive Truth Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting ſome Modern, or New Abuſes, of that which is ſo much Pleaded for, and ſo little Underſtood, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> IN A SERMON Preached in the Church of <hi>Bridport</hi> within the County of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the Forenoon, being <hi>November</hi> 3. 1672. before the Magiſtrates of that Burrough.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Rich. Luce,</hi> a Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by Law Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rowland Reynolds</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51655:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51655:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend, and his much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friend and Neighbour, Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Godwyn</hi> Rector of <hi>Bridport.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our benevolent Admiſſion of me to Preach in your Church, to gratifie my good Friend Mr. <hi>George Spen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> one of the preſent Bayliffs of your Town, hath put me up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a little more Labour then I expected. Yet I do not ſo much lay the blame upon your Admiſſion, which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce free from blame; as upon the over-imprudence of ſome, whoſe Tongues being liquoured with the Oyle of Confidence, have charged me with Rayling againſt the <hi>Kings</hi> Churches in my Sermon. An odious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumely indeed. What! for a ſon of the <hi>Church of England</hi> to revile the Gods, and ſpeak evil of the Ruler of his People? To fault the Edicts of his Soveraigne, The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Countrey: And in a word, the the nurſing Father of this Church? <hi>Sir,</hi> now
<pb facs="tcp:51655:3"/>I declare unto you plainely, whom I am bound notwithſtanding to honour as a Father; that you are highly concern'd. Concern'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that you would let me paſs unchaſtiſed for profaning your Pulpit by ſo rude a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, wherein as is reported, I was ſo unpardonably faulty. But <hi>Sir,</hi> ſeeing it is the uſual practiſe of thoſe who neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their duty to God, or the <hi>King,</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and traduce with all malice imaginable thoſe who hinder the building of their <hi>Babel:</hi> I am reſolved, in ſteed of any other Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, to expoſe my Sermon to your own judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Examination. And leſt you ſhould be thought to be over partial to your friend, I know not what you can doe leſs, then bring the Authour and his Sermon to a fair Trial. So without any more wordes; when you have peruſed the Sermon which was preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your ſelf, If you think it worth the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, you may doe as you think fit with it, and in order thereunto you may Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Chediock, <date>
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 18. 1672.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt affectionate Friend and Fellow-labourer in the ſervice of God, King, and Church,</hi> Richard Luce.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51655:3"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful, and Loyal Bayliffs and Magiſtrates of the Borrough of <hi>Bridport,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> Salvation in Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here preſent that Sermon unto your eyes, which was Preached unto your Ears in your Pariſh Church, on the <hi>3d.</hi> of this inſtant <hi>November.</hi> I might have ſaved my ſelf and you that labour, had not ſome Tongues charged me with railing at the Kings Church; for ſome ſo are pleaſed to call their New Erected Congregations in Contradiſtinction to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Eſtabliſhed by the known Laws of this famous Kingdome. <hi>Sirs,</hi> If I have ſpoken amiſs in any part, or parcel of the enſuing diſcourſe, bear witneſs againſt me: but if I have diſcharged my Conſcience ſo far as became a Loyal Subject to his Majeſty, and an obedient Son of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> no way Thwarting his Majeſties Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in indulging his loving Subjects, and wherein Himſelf hath declared his expreſs Reſolution, Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Intention to be, That, the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be preſerved, and remain entire in its Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Government, as now it ſtands Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb facs="tcp:51655:4"/>by Law. And this be taken to be, as it is, the Baſis, Rule, and Standard of the general and publick worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You will be pleaſed to take this my humble Proſtration of this enſuing Sermon, as a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere acknowledgment of my Obedience to his Majeſty, and all that are put in Authority under him, both in Church and State; and as a pledg of my hearty love to the publick Peace, as well as to your ſelves, whom with all that call upon the Name of the Lord Jeſus. Chriſt in ſincerity, I commend to your gracious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and protection of Almighty God, in whom I Reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Chediock,</hi> Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>
                     <date>the 18th. 1672.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate Friend and Servant, <hi>R. Luce.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51655:4"/>
            <head>CHRISTIAN LIBERTY Not to be ABUSED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 Pet. 2.16</bibl> 
                  <hi>As free, and not uſing your</hi> (or as the Original imports) <hi>not having the Liberty for a Cloak of Malitiouſneſs, but as the Servants of God.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that goeth about to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a Multitude (ſaith the moſt renowned and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <hi>Hooker</hi>) that they are not ſo well Governed as they ought to be,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Richard Hooker,</hi> lib. 1. Eccleſ. Polit. pag. 1.</note> ſhall never want attentive and favourable Hearers. Which comes to paſs, (as that learned and godly Divine obſerved) becauſe they know the manifold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51655:5"/>whereunto every kind of Regiment is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; whiles yet they have not the Judgment to conſider the ſecret Letts and Impediments, or Difficulties, which in publick proceedings are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable and inevitable. And becauſe (as he adds) ſuch as reprove ſuppoſed diſorders of ſtate, are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for principal friends to the common benefit of all; and for men that carry a ſingular freedome of mind under this plauſible pretext, whatſoever they utter, paſſeth for good and currant. That which wanteth in the waight of their ſpeech, is ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the aptneſs of mens minds to accept and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; whereas on the other ſide, if we maintain things that are eſtabliſhed, we have not only to ſtrive with a number of heavy prejudices rooted in the hearts of men, who think, that herein, we ſerve the Time, and ſpeak in favour of the preſent State for our own advantages, but alſo to bear ſuch exceptions, as minds ſo prepoſſeſſed with prejudice, uſually take againſt that which they are loath ſhould be poured into them.</p>
            <p>However, it may happen to my ſelf at this time in ſuch a Chryſis of diſtempered humours in the minds, both of the <hi>Maſculine</hi> and <hi>Faeminine</hi> Gender, I ſhall not be curiouſly inquiſitive.</p>
            <p>Though I durſt not ſtand in <hi>Corahs</hi> Tents, nor with his Rebellious Aſſociates, affront <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the King and the Prieſt, Prince and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with, Ye take too much upon you, ſeeing all the Congregation is holy: And though I preſume
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51655:5"/>not in the leaſt to Cavil againſt Acts of Parliament, nor Edicts of Council-Table, nor rudely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt my Superiours or their ſanctions, to vent crude Politicks, and impoſe them upon the Weak and Credulous: Yet as the caſe ſtands, you cannot take it amiſs at his hands, who hath very much Charity for your Souls, if whiles he beſpeaks you as Chriſts Free-men; yet admoniſheth you in the Language, not of himſelf, but of the Holy Ghoſt, by bleſſed St. <hi>Peter</hi> in my Text, as free, and not uſing (or not having) the liberty for a Cloak of Malitiouſneſs, but as the Servants of God.</p>
            <p>If you look back into the precedent part of this Epiſtle, you will find the Apoſtle ſetting forth the Priviledges and Dignity of our high and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly calling of Chriſtianity. For that we are a Choſen Generation, a Royal Prieſthood, an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by reaſon of our Redemption pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by Chriſt Jeſus our Lord. To this end compare the 9th. verſe of this Chapter, out of which my Text is ſelected with the firſt Chapter throughout, eſpecially with the 18th. and 19th. <hi>verſes, &amp;c.</hi> of that ſame Chapter.</p>
            <p>Now leſt that theſe priviledges ſhould make us grow Proud and Inſolent, and forgetful of our duty towards men, under pretence of our near Relation unto God: The bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> after he had preſſed the Exerciſe of our Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, both in abſtaining from, and utter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51655:6"/>and Deteſtation of all fleſhly Luſts, and Infernal Powers which War againſt the Soul; as alſo in leading of an honeſt and upright Life and Converſation amongſt the very Gentiles, to the glory of God, and the vindication of the Doctrine of the Goſpel of Chriſt, from the virulent Tongues of all malitious Detractors, and pernicious Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniators, <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
            <p>He proceeds in eſpecial manner to give us di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, ſo well as command, concerning ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſubjection, and obedience to all lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governours as ſent by him for the puniſhment of Evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well, <hi>verſe</hi> 13, 14. and to this purpoſe he adds his Reaſon, <hi>verſe</hi> 15. For ſo is the Will of God, that with well doing, ye ſhould put to ſilence the Ignorance of Fooliſh men, and not without need; ſeeing that no ſooner was the Chriſtian Religion planted in the World, but on a ſudden the Prince of Darkneſs, the Devil, and Satan, finding his Dominion broken and routed, endeavoured by all means poſſible to diſturb the free and happy paſſage of the Goſpel, both by procuring open Perſecutions to be raiſed againſt the Church, and true Profeſſors of our moſt holy Chriſtian Religion; as alſo by raiſing and ſtirring up di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers falſe Brethren from at home, and within the very bowels of the Church, who ſpake and vented divers perverſe things, both contrary to the Dectrine and Fundamental grounds of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51655:6"/>holy Chriſtian Faith, ſo well as to the Peace and tranquillity of the Communion of Saints. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had he any device more apt for his purpoſe, then a pretence that Chriſtianity was deſtructive to Magiſtracy, whereby he incenſed all that were in Authority, with a very ſevere jealouſy againſt the Truth of Chriſt, though yet our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, had declared openly, <hi>that his Kingdom was not of this World, John</hi> 18.36. But of all the Impoſtors that ever I meet with in this kind, I find none more notorious and dangerous, then <hi>Simon Magus:</hi> who, (as the Learned and Pious Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> notes in his Proenical diſſertati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning Anti-Chriſt, Chapter the ninth) was the ring-leader of the Sect of the <hi>Gnoſticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is he who in the Acts of the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Chap. 8, 10. was held in high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem amongſt the People, who blaſphemouſly called him the great power of God. By him they had been long and long deceived, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched with Sorceries and Magical. Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And now he finding his Trade of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſturage, or Couſenage, to decay by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of Chriſtianity, this very <hi>Simon</hi> enrolls himſelf under the Banner of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt by Baptiſm, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Simon</hi> himſelf (ſaith that Scripture) believed alſo, and when he was baptized, he continued with <hi>Phillip, &amp;c.</hi> This he did as appears by the Sequel of that Chapter, not ſo much out of any true. zeal, or love, which he did bear towards Chriſtianity,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51655:7"/>as in hopes to have made a gainful Trade of it: For when he ſaw that his expectation was fruſtrated this way, he with his Followers, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the way of Chriſt; and firſt of all, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſht all the Orthodox, and pure Profeſſors of the Chriſtian faith; and by this Schiſm, they break the Union of the Church. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>They went out from us,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, Second Chapter, ninteenth Verſe. Neither would they remain any longer in the boſome of the holy Chriſtian Catholick and Apoſtolick Church. And thence having broken the Churches Unity, they did forthwith caſt off all Charity towards their Brethren, and Fellow Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>From whence the Apoſtle and beloved Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of our Lord concludes, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the ſecond Chapter of that Epiſtle, Ver. 9. That however they did pretend to greater light and knowledg in Heavenly Miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then others; yet that they were a Company of ſelf-conceited, blind, ſottiſh, and prodigious ignorants. Hence ſaith Saint <hi>John, He that loveth not, knoweth not God: for God is love. And he that ſaith, he is in the light, and hateth his Brother, is in darkneſs; even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, againſt theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kites,</hi> rather then <hi>Gnoſticks;</hi> Ignorants, rather then Perſons of Knowledg; we find both Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51655:7"/>Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> Saint <hi>John,</hi> and Saint <hi>Jude,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting their diſcourſes throughout their ſeveral Epiſtles. Amongſt many others, take that in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3. <hi>&amp;c. If any man teach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and conſent not unto the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to godlineſs, He is proud, knowing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: but doting about queſtions, and ſtrifes, of words whereof cometh Envy, Strife, Railings, Evil-ſurmiſings, perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt minds, and deſtitute of the truth, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that Gain is Godlineſs: from ſuch with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw thy ſelf.</hi> Such men theſe were, <hi>who turned the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, Jude</hi> the fourth verſe. Inſomuch that they denyed the only Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Theſe were the Monſters, in the ſaith of whom, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> fore-warns the Chriſtian flock, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>There ſhall be falſe Teachers amongſt you, who ſhall privily bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord. that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction. And many ſhall follow their pernicious wayes; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of whom, the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of. And through Covetuouſneſs ſhall they, with feigned words, make Merchandiſe of you: whoſe judgement now of a long time lingreth not, and their damnation ſlumbereth not.</hi> Theſe were the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avening <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or devouring Wolves, of whom our Saviour ſpeaks, <hi>Matih.</hi> 7.15. <hi>And the falſe Chriſts that ſhould come and deceive many, Matth.</hi> 24.24. Thoſe are the Dogs Saint <hi>Paul</hi> bids
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51655:8"/>us beware of,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>This</hi> Ignatius <hi>was, as is ſaid, that Child which our Lord took up in his own Armes,</hi> Mar. 10 13. Euſeb. lib. 1. Eccleſ. Hiſt.</note> in <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.2. And <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ravening Doggs.</hi> Theſe are the Conciſion; becauſe, whiles they feigned themſelves to be <hi>Jews (i. e.)</hi> Circumciſed, and Zealots for the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical Circumciſion; yet did they not keep the Law, but only under this pretence, tear in pieces the Church of Chriſt: And therefore it is moſt plain what St. <hi>Peter</hi> drives at, both in my Text, and in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. when he ſaith, <hi>The time is come that Judgment maſt begin at the Houſe of God,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>wherein the more Orthodox and purer Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Profeſſors of the Holy Catholick Faith were to ſuffer all manner of Evils, both from the</hi> Jews <hi>and</hi> Gnoſticks, <hi>for the ſake of the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Juſtin Martyr in Queſt. &amp; Reſponſ ad Orthodoxos.</note> For as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> notes, It was uſual for the Hereticks of thoſe times, to Condemn thoſe that would not ſay, and think as they did. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Valedictory. Sermon to the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>grievous Wolves,</hi> Act. 20. who by their Heretical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and Seditious practiſes did make ſpoyle of the Flock of Chriſt. For whiles they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended nothing more than <hi>Liberty,</hi> they did the more entangle themſelves and their followers in the bondage of Corruption, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18, 19. And hence four Principal Errours in thoſe Gnoſticks offer themſelves to Correction ſo well as Obſervation.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51655:8"/>
            <p>Firſt: Their Magical Enchantments.</p>
            <p>Secondly: Their allowance of all manner of Senſualities, and fleſhly Luſts, and mixtures, even to the Community, or rather deſilement of the Marriage-Bed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly: Their Exempting themſelves from the Yoke of all Authority, both Civil and Sacred.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly: They held Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to avoid Perſecution for the Croſs of Chriſt. By all which they proſtituted the Holy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, both in its Doctrinals and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votionals, Morals, and Evangelicals to ſhame and contempt, under pretence of Liberty. And to hold you no longer from the deſign of our Apoſtle in my Text, St. <hi>Peter</hi> here wipes off the Reproach which theſe Impoſtors endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to caſt upon the Name of Chriſt, under pretence of Liberty purchaſed by him; when he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>As free, and not uſing, or not having the Liberty for a Cloak of Malitiouſneſs, but as the Servants of God.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may hear our Apoſtle ſpeaking unto us to this effect; namely, Let none of you whom Chriſt hath purchaſed by his moſt precious blood, to enjoy ſo many high and eminent priviledges, as to be an Holy Nation, a Royal Prieſt-hood, a peculiar people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Think that hereby you are exempted from your duties, whether with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51655:9"/>reference towards God in the duties of the firſt Table, or towards men, required in the duties of the ſecond Table of the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to the performance of all which, we are firmly bound by Divine injunction. In eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner, aſſure your ſelves, that the Doctrine of Chriſtianity teacheth nothing more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, then that you ought to ſubmit your ſelves unto every Ordinance of man, for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governours, as ſent by him for the puniſhment of Evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well; for ſo is the Will of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If you plead your Freedome; know that your Freedome, in, and by Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, doth not conſiſt in believing, and living as you liſt your ſelves; nor in any exemption from Obedience unto lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. No! For our Lord himſelf, though Heir in Right to the Crown and Scepter of <hi>Judah,</hi> by temporal diſcent from the loynes of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> ſo well as Prince of the Kings of the Earth by his Eternal Power and God-head; yet ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he would give occaſion of offence whiles he was living, or leave a ſuſpicious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of any ill-meaning in his Doctrine or practice after his departure from this world (as to Perſonal or Corporeal preſence) Himſelf I ſay, would rather work a Miracle, and pay Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for himſelf and <hi>Peter,</hi> Math. 17.25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the end of that Chapter. To ſhew that his Diſciples after him, under no pretence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51655:9"/>whatſoever, ſhould plead immunity in that or the like Caſe: much leſs may any Chriſtian under any pretence of Liberty, vail or cover o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Treaſonable Imaginations or Practiſes againſt their Superiours; but as Holy Church hath taught us devoutly to Pray, ſo let us be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to practiſe, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> We muſt faithfully ſerve, honour, and humbly obey the King, and all that are put in Authority under him, in, and for the Lord, according to his bleſſed Word and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: As duly conſidering that the King is Gods Vice-gerent, and that all other Magiſtrates, who are Commiſſionated by, and under him, do bear derivatively and ſubordinately an Impreſs of the Divine Image and Superſcription; <hi>As free, and not having the Liberty for a Cloak of Malitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but as the Servants of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Obſervations offer themſelves to our Conſideration out of this Portion of Holy Writ, but I ſhall confine my ſelf to ſhew you briefly.</p>
            <p>Firſt: What Chriſtian Liberty is, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it doth conſiſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly: How it ought not to be abuſed as a Cloak or Covering of any lewd Principles or wicked Practiſes. And for the better help of your memories, I ſhall reduce both into one Doctrine or Propoſition.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51655:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> That it is altogether inconſiſtent with, and contrariant unto the Holy Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the Profeſſors thereof, under pretence of Liberty to Cloak and colour over Malice and Wickedneſs. Or more briefly, Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt not be Abuſed to any wicked practiſes; eſpecially againſt lawful Authority.</p>
            <p>This poſition flowes naturally from the Text, which is inſerted by way of Anticipation to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent an obvious Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If we are Chriſts Freemen <hi>(i. e.)</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed and Redeemed by his moſt precious Blood, and free Denizons of Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or ſubjection do we owe to any perſon, or power upon Earth, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> The Apoſtle Anſwers this by ſhewing,
<note place="margin">Solut.</note> from the Rule of correlatives, what our Chriſtian Liberty is, and wherein it doth conſiſt: For,</p>
            <p>Our Chriſtian Liberty is this;
<note place="margin">Quaenam ſit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertas Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana.</note> namely, that we being delivered from the hands of our Enemies <hi>(i. e.)</hi> from Sin, Hell, and Satan; we ſhould ſerve God truly in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs all the days of our lives, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74, 75. So that if any one would be informed, what's our Liberty? my anſwer would be: It is a Freedom to ſerve God; to obſerve and do what he hath commanded us. This is the ſum and ſcope of the Goſpel of Chriſt: to teach us to walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Vocation wherewith we are called,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51655:10"/>
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.1. ſo <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. The Grace of God which bringeth Salvation, hath appeared unto all men, teaching us, that denying Ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts, we ſhould live Soberly, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and Godly in this preſent World: and this in eſpecial manner is one way whereby we vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the honour of our high and holy Calling, and ſhew forth the praiſes of him that hath called us out of darkneſs into his marvellous light; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by ſubmitting our ſelves unto every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake; whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governours, as ſent by him, <hi>&amp;c. As free, and not having Liberty for a Cloak of Malitiouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Freemen we are indeed! But we muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that the Liberty of the Lords Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in this life, is ſpiritual and inward; not bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and outward, until the life to come. And therefore the beſt definition which can be given of our Chriſtian Liberty, with relation unto this preſent life, is that which our Holy Mother, the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath taught us, and fitted to my hands in her Collect for peace, where-after ſhe teacheth us to pray; <hi>O God who art the Author of Peace, and Lover of Concord in knowledg, of whom ſtandeth our Eternal Life;</hi> ſhe addeth, <hi>whoſe Service is perfect Freedome:</hi> whence it is eaſie to define, That the ſervice of God, is the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans perfect Freedom, or Liberty in this preſent world; or, a Chriſtians moſt perfect Liberty in this world, is Gods ſervice; and this is agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51655:11"/>to the Apoſtolical Dialect in my Text, where St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls Chriſtians, Gods Servants, or the Servants of God. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> takes it as the heighth of his glory on this ſide of Heaven, that he had God for his Witneſs, whom he ſerved with his Spirit in the Goſpel of his Son, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9. and good reaſon, ſeeing, as he ſaith elſe-where, <hi>Where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is Liberty,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. And ſurely Beloved, it was never better with Chriſtianity, then when <hi>Pliny</hi> the Heathen wrote to <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plinius</hi> Junior</note> to whom he could give no other deſcription of her Profeſſors, than that they did riſe before day, and ſing Hymnes unto Chriſt, whom they Worſhipped as God; and for better diſcipline among them, they prohibited Murther, Theft, Adultery, Fraud, Rebellion, Perfidiouſneſs, and the denyal of goods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their truſt, with other ſuch like diſhoneſt and ungodly pranks. And for this Reaſon, <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his ſecond Apology for the Chriſtians in his time, complains of over-hard meaſure and uſage againſt the poor Chriſtians, in that after the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Devils had produced ſome men, who affirmed themſelves to be Gods; and thoſe, ſaith he, of you Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Not only do not ſuffer Perſecution, but are dignified with Honours and Promotions. In a word then, the Holineſs of Chriſtianity, is ſuch, that it doth not admit ſo much as an evil thought againſt the Magiſtrate, whether Supream or Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought, nor the Rich in thy bed-chamber, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was good
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51655:11"/>Doctrine in <hi>Solomons</hi> dayes, and is, and ſhould be ſo in ours, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20. It forbids all irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſpeeches towards them, or concerning them. Hence St. <hi>Paul</hi> corrects himſelf, <hi>Act.</hi> 23.5. I wiſt not, Brethren, that he was the High Prieſt; for it is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of thy people;</hi> and concerning Reſiſtance of them by Treaſonable Plots, or open Armes, there can be nothing more directly ſaid againſt it, than what the Holy Ghoſt hath left upon Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Record, under the hand of the ſame Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 13.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>Let every Soul be ſubject unto the Higher Powers; for, there is no power but of God; the Powers that be, are Ordain'd of God. Whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God; and they that reſiſt, purchaſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Damnation.</q> We have frequent inſtances to this purpoſe of Gods juſtice in cutting off Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels from the Land of the Living; we ſee it in <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> Numb. 16. at large. <hi>Who ever took the Sword in hand,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 20.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 King. 1. &amp; 2. Chapters.</note> without Gods Command, but he periſhed by it? What</hi> She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, <hi>or</hi> Adonijah, <hi>ever blew a Trumpet of Sedition, or Rebellion, but they did this againſt their own lives? When</hi> David <hi>would have ſpared Rebellions</hi> Abſolom,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> The Lord cauſed him to be hung in the mid'ſt of an Oak, between Heaven and Earth, as unworthy of either, becauſe he Rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Royal Father: Yea, Wicked <hi>Jezabel</hi> had ſo much obſerved the method of Divine Juhice, that ſhe could demand boldly, <hi>Had</hi> Zimri <hi>Peace, who ſlew his Maſter?</hi> 2 King. 9.31. Our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51655:12"/>own Chronicles (as Doctor <hi>Thomas Taylor</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved long agoe) are full of rare examples of Gods judgments,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Taylor, <hi>in his Comentary on</hi> Tit. 2.1.</note> upon not a few of ſuch Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Miſcreants. The ſtrange diſcovery of the <hi>Percyes</hi> Conſpiracy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Elder-Eiſhop</hi> Carle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's <hi>thankful remembrance of Gods mercy.</hi>
               </note> and that of the <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder Treaſon,</hi> are ſuch remarkable Monuments of Gods Vengeance againſt Traytors, as may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be forgotten, to the perpetual ſhame of the new Romiſh-Religion; but will ſtand upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, (unleſs Poſterity be over-ungrateful) to the end of Time. Neither let that unparalled Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, committed againſt the Sacred blood of our late Royal Martyr King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt, of bleſſed Memory, nor the juſt vengeance of God upon the Actours, in that horrid Tragedy, be ever blotted out from under Heaven. Neither is this only an humane invention, or obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but an infallible extract, and concluſion expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet down in the Holy Scriptures of Almighty God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21, 22. <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change,</hi> or with the ſeditious. <hi>For their deſtruction ſhall ariſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were I minded to common-place it at large on this Theam, I ſhould be over-burthenſome to your patience: wherefore for brevities ſake, I ſhall lay down, two or three of the moſt perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Arguments, to preſs home what hath been ſaid, and ſo proceed to the Application.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51655:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. God himſelf hath ordained Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>By me Kings raign, and Princes decree juſtice, Prov.</hi> 8.15. So <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.14. That the moſt High hath power over the Kingdoms of men, and giveth them to whomſoever He will. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> layeth it down for good Chriſtian Doctrine, <hi>the Powers that be, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dained of God, Rom.</hi> 13.1. Who then can without prodigious guilt take the ſword out of the Princes hand? or deprive him of that which he owes to none but God himſelf alone, namely, his Crown and his Life?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2d. God hath been pleaſed to honour them with his own Name, whom he hath raiſed up unto place of Authority; that ſo they might be had in due honour, and eſteem, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their place and dignity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods, and all of ye children of the. moſt high.</hi> Wherefore how durſt any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume without horrid impudence, to affront, or withſtand, thoſe whom the King of Heaven hath ſo highly honoured? <hi>Note,</hi> only let the Magiſtrate here remember, that though he be as it were a God by Office, yet that he is but a man by Eſſence; and therefore I may be bold to put you in mind of that too, <hi>Ye ſhall dye like men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 3. God ſetteth a ſtamp upon Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, no leſs then an Impreſſe of his own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, Mercy, Juſtice, and Wiſdome on thoſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Deities, and little Gods on Earth; yea, a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51655:13"/>great part of his Image ſhineth upon every one of them. As for inſtance, let me begin with the State of Soveraign Princes. And here what a radiant body of a kind of Omnipotent Splendour, like as in the ſolar beams, diſplayes it ſelf, and ſpreads its rayes, from the Seat and Throne of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty? both in that ſo many Hundred Thouſands are ſubjected to the power of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and in that, the whole adminiſtration of a numerous People is in one hand, and that the good eſtate of all, dependeth on one alone under God. So the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Magiſtrates, or rather, thoſe whom the Soveraign Power of the Prince, hath put in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under him, according to the Laws, and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, Cuſtomes and Conſtitutions of his Realms. Thoſe, I ſay, by virtue of their Commiſſions, and Charters, receive a kind of an Impreſs of the Princeſs Majeſty and Authority, which as loyal Subjects, and faithful Adminiſtrators, of Law, and Juſtice, they are to improve for the glory of God, the preſervation of the publick peace, according to the Laws of God, and the known Laws of the Realm. And who then is that Son of <hi>Belial,</hi> that durſt ſet himſelf in oppoſition to ſo ſolemn and ſacred a ſanction? or what compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of men, durſt violate ſo Divine a conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Surely God will take this one day, as an high affront done to himſelf: and if any will be ſo impudent as to deſpiſe their Superiours, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State, they may exſpect to hear. that in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7. applyed againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>They have not rejected Thee, (i. e.)</hi> the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51655:13"/>lawful Superiour, <hi>But they have rejected me, that I ſhould not raign over them.</hi> God takes the diſhonour which is done to thoſe, whom he hath placed in Authority over us, as done to himſelf; and this Refractory, diſobedients ſhall know one day, both to their great grief, and extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt horrour; unleſs God of his infinite mercy, grant them repentance, unto the humble and hearty acknowledgment and amendment of their moſt lew'd and wicked <hi>Errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But what need all this adoe? <hi>Ad quid perditio haec?</hi> To what end is all this waſt? we are Freemen, we have a liberty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſerve God according to our Conſcience, and what hath any man to ſay againſt it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solut.</hi> Ay! and have you a Liberty indeed? A Liberty, I ſay? Well ſaid. But for what I pray you? What! to ſay and do what you liſt? I hope not ſo. But if any of you durſt think ſo, or take it ſo: I pray God you may ſee your miſtake in time before it be too late. You have a Liberty you ſay, to ſerve God according to your Conſcience. I pray God when He ſhall call us all to a ſtrict accompt, and reckoning, that, that ſame thing which ſome call Conſcience, do not appear to be meer Humour and Obſtinacy. For they can ſhew us no grounds in all the World, why their <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſmes</hi> ſhould be called the ſervice of God. And now I am come ſo far; as to meet ſome who are hugely taken up with their New-erected
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51655:14"/>Meetings, neither may I baulk them; though I muſt tell you, I quarrel not with his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Indulgence: yet I cannot chuſe, but pitty their ignorance, who ſo manifeſtly abuſe it. For let me demand of any Perſon breathing, who diſlikes the publick communion of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> that refuſe to joyn with us in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and praiſes, in the ſervice of God, appointed in this Church, in the hearing of the Word of God read and preached, and in the participation of the bleſſed Sacraments? I pray you upon what terms do you hold Communion one with another, in your New erected Congregations, or Societies, if you do not openly and ſolemnly declare in the ſame ſocieties, and ſolemn Meetings of yours, That you do <hi>renounce the Devil and all his Works, the Pomps and Vanities of the wicked World, all the ſinful luſts of the fleſh, all the carnal deſires of the ſame,</hi> ſo as not to follow, nor be lead by them? do you profeſs openly, and ſolemnly, your belief of all the <hi>Articles of the holy Chriſtian Faith?</hi> And do your Speakers read unto you the Moral Law? Do they call you to the obedience of Gods holy will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements? And do they preſs you earneſtly to walk in the ſame all the dayes of your lives? do they preſs you, and call upon you, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs dayly and hourly your ſins unto Almighty God, with an humble, lowly, penitent and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient heart; to the end, that you may obtain forgiveneſs of the ſame by his infinite goodneſs and mercy? do they teach you to pray, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51655:14"/>ſue earneſtly and heartily, for the pardon of the many breaches and violations of Gods Law, whereof you ſtand guilty before him, and in the Courts of your own Conſcienes? do they teach you to pray unto God, in and through the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and mediation of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt for his ſpecial grace, that He will <hi>incline your hearts to keep his Laws,</hi> better for the time to come.</p>
            <p>For mine own part, I do declare my ſelf free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all the World, how indifferent ſoever, I am contented to be accounted in other matters, which are but meerly circumſtantial and arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable by common Authority; yet without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to any Perſon, or Party, I do ſolemnly declare it in the preſence of God, and in the face of this Chriſtian Congregation, That I cannot ſee good grounds for my ſelf, or any other Perſon profeſſing Chriſtianity, to hold Communion with any Society whatſoever, where the People are not put in continual remembrance of the <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> which they have made with God in their <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> where they have neither <hi>Creed,</hi> nor <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> nor <hi>Ten Commandements,</hi> nor the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> expounded: much leſs the ſame Sacraments, I mean of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and the Lords Supper, adminiſtred accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order and form, the judgment and practice of the Primitive Church. For how can I, or any man or woman, ſeriouſly and in good earneſt profeſſing Chriſtianity, venture our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51655:15"/>in ſuch a Communion, where the faith once delivered unto the Saints, is not openly confeſſed with the mouth, ſo well as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to believe it in their hearts? eſpecially, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great Apoſtle ſpeaks it ſo plainly, <hi>That with the Heart Man believeth unto righteouſneſs, and with the mouth confeſſion of faith is made unto Salvation, Rom.</hi> 10.10.</p>
            <p>I abhor ſuch fooliſh Whimſes, to ſay no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and ſuch horrid and dangerous <hi>Enthuſiaſmes,</hi> to call them no worſe, which prefer every odd and idle fancy of any particular man or Miniſter whatſoever, to the received Doctrine and Practice of the Univerſal or holy Catholick Church. And ſo much the more for that the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> tells us plainly, that, no Propheſy of Scripture is of any private interpretation or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. And ſurely, if it be an abſurd impoſition of the Council, or rather Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Trent,</hi> to change the Rule of the Chriſtian Faith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 4.</note> by Equiparating unwritten Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Decreto</hi> 1.</note> with the very written word of God, can we judge it leſs abſurd in our Novelliſts at home, who will have ſo many Creeds, as Heads, though never ſo contradictory each to other. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, ſaith Saint <hi>Jude,</hi> when I gave all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to write unto you of the Common Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; it was needful for me to write unto you, and exhort you that you ſhould earneſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the faith which was once delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the Saints, <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. It was ever held
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51655:15"/>for a good Rule, whereby to underſtand the legality of any practice, or to try the truth of any Doctrine, which <hi>Vincentius Lerinenſis</hi> gives. <hi>Id tenendum quod ſemper, quod ubique, quod ab omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Creditum eſt, Id tandem facimus, ſi ſequamur Antiquitatem, Univerſalitatem, Conſenſum.</hi> That is to be held, which hath been believed alwayes, every where, and of all. And that we do, if we follow Antiquity, Univerſality and Conſent.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Simon Magus, Ebion, Cerinthus, Menander, Carpocrates,</hi> with the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> &amp; other hereticks, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the communion of the holy Catholick Church, <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> tells us what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of them;
<note place="margin">Juſtin Martyr Secunda Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia per Chriſtianis.</note> how they ran into thoſe exceſſes that the followers of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> worſhipped him as the Son of God that appeared unto the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Samaria.</hi> And <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> after <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Irenaeus, <hi>lib.</hi> 1, <hi>cap.</hi> 20.</note> ſaith, that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> is ſaid to be honoured of <hi>Claudius Caeſar;</hi> of many he was glorified as God; he Taught, that himſelf was he, who, as the Son appeared amongſt the Jews, that in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> he deſcended as the Father, and amongſt other Nations, he came as the Holy Ghoſt. That himſelf alſo was the higheſt Power, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> him who above and over all things, is the Father, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſo exalting himſelf above all that is called God, he alſo ſuffered himſelf to be called whatſoever men called him, Who is the Father Eternal. Moreover that his Trull <hi>Helena,</hi> whom he called his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or prime conceit, or principle did with him generate Angels and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51655:16"/>of whom he alſo ſaid, that this world was made; that according to his Grace men were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; that the God of the <hi>Jews</hi> was one of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels Created by him the ſaid <hi>Simon;</hi> and the ſaid Holy Father St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in his 22 Chapter of his firſt book againſt Hereſies, chargeth the aforeſaid <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> to have ſaid, <hi>that he was the only Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who hath made Angels and Arch-Angels, Virtues and Powers; that his Picture or Figure was made according to the figure of</hi> Jupiter, <hi>and of</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena (<hi>or without doubt of</hi> Helena, <hi>as Dr.</hi> Hammond <hi>notes</hi>) <hi>after the figure of</hi> Minerva; and theſe were to be worſhipped, <hi>Chap.</hi> 21. So <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>Tractate de Anima,</hi> or of the Soul, tells us, <hi>How that</hi> Simon Magus <hi>was called of his followers, The Higheſt or Soveraign Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved, I beſeech you in the bowels of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to conſider with your ſelves the dangerous and pernicious conſequents of making Rents and Schiſmes in the body of Chriſt, which is the Church. It is a wonder if the Schiſmatick do find center till he become an obſtinate Heretick, or deſperate Blaſphemer; witneſs that of <hi>Hacket,</hi> who at his very Execution in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> died Blaſpheming. What ſhould I ſpeak of others in our own times? know, that out of Church, there is no Salvation. That the Church is known to be a true Spouſe of Chriſt, by that Faith and true Allegiance which ſhe bears unto Chriſt. This Faith is the Faith of Chriſt Crucified, which ſhe is not aſhamed to confeſs with open mouth in the face of all the world. Into this Faith ſhe Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51655:16"/>all them whom ſhe liſteth under the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. In the defence of this faith, which our holy Mother the Church of <hi>England</hi> profeſſeth, at this time dyed all the holy Apoſtles and Martyrs, <hi>viz.</hi> Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Saint <hi>James,</hi> Saint <hi>John,</hi> and Saint <hi>Jude,</hi> and all the reſt of the Apoſtles. This is that ſame faith which was born witneſs unto by the firſt four General Councils. Namely,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Council of</hi> Nice <hi>conſiſting of</hi> 318. <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Anno Dom. 326.</note> the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice,</hi> called under <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, wherein <hi>Arius</hi> and his adherents, who denyed the Divinity of the Son of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of</hi> Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople 400. <hi>Biſhops and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi> Anno Dom. 383.</note> were condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for Hereticks. So the Council of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> holden fourty years after that firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice,</hi> under the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Elder, againſt <hi>Macedonius</hi> the Heretick, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the God-head of the Holy Ghoſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of</hi> Epheſus 200 <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Anno. Dom. 451.</note> And the firſt of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> ſummoned by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Younger, againſt <hi>Neſtorious,</hi> who affirmed two Perſons in Chriſt. Laſtly, the Council of <hi>Calcedon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>At</hi> Calcedon 600 <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Anno Dom. 451.</note> called and convened under <hi>Martian</hi> the Emperour, againſt <hi>Eutyches,</hi> who aſſerted that there was but one Nature in Chriſt, made up of the Divine and Humane.</p>
            <p>All theſe Councils held and determined the ſame moſt holy Faith; which is received in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which we have in our Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, or Publick Service, under the Names and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of the Apoſtles, <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creeds. In the defence and maintenance hereof, dyed the renowned Saint <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> Saint <hi>Cyprian,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51655:17"/>Iereuaeus,</hi> and other the Holy and Learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Primitive Church. And to come nearer home to our own times,
<note place="margin">Cranmer <hi>was Arch Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury. Ridley <hi>Biſhop of</hi> London. Latimer <hi>of</hi> Worceſter. Hooper <hi>of</hi> Gloceſter. Farrar <hi>of St.</hi> Davids.</note> theſe Goly Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Biſhops, <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Hooper, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar,</hi> and thoſe Godly Miniſters alſo, <hi>Saunders, Taylor, Bradford,</hi> and many others under the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Perſecution, ſealed this ſame holy Primitive Catholick and Apoſtolick Faith, with their dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt heart-blood.</p>
            <p>Not to trouble you with the inſtances of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faithful Confeſſours, and Martyrs, of a more Modern date, whoſe blood cannot chuſe, but run freſh in moſt of our Memories.</p>
            <p>All theſe I aſſure you dyed in the ſame faith, which our Church hath taught us, and doth ſtill continue in teaching us to believe: though here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto too many I fear in our times, who would be thought, to be ſomewhat more wiſe then their Neighbours, are too great Strangers. This is that Faith upon which our Church is built, and againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prevaile.</p>
            <p>Though the Church be ſhaken by many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions and diſorders: yet her Faith, the beſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hae revelatio Patris eſt: hoc Eccleſiae fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum eſt: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aec ſecuritas aeternitatis eſt. Hinc Regni coelorum habet clavem 2 hinc terrena ejus judicia coeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a ſunt.</hi> Hillac. <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de Trinit.</hi>
               </note> ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Eternity, is not ſhaken. No! that remains ſtill the ſame, and ſo will do by the grace of God, until the Angel in the Revelation ſhall proclaim that time ſhall be no more. And now to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51655:17"/>
            <p>If any will forſake our Communion, while we ſtand upon theſe terms, I may juſtly ſay of them, as Saint <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaid of the old <hi>Gnaſticks,</hi> and Diſciples of Old <hi>Simon</hi> the Witch, once and again before mentioned, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. If they had been true and genuine branches of God the Father, they would never have been Enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But if in nothing elſe, I may prevail with thoſe who do diſſent from us; yet let them be perſwaded whiles they have a Liberty, not to uſe it, or rather not to abuſe it as a Cloak of Malitiouſneſs, Treaſon, or Rebellion; nor to Maintain any lewed Principles: nor to ſet on foot any Malignant Practiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, or the King; Church, or State, Friends or Foes; But rather as becometh good Chriſtians, ſo let them demean themſelves in all Places, and upon all occaſions, and amongſt all Companies as the Servants of God. <hi>As free, and not uſing,</hi> or not having <hi>the Liberty for a Cloak of Malitiouſneſs, but as the Servants of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know you expect ſomwhat to be ſaid unto Perſons in Authority, by way of Advice; but I have not had time to tumble over a Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance according to the new mode of thoſe who are hugely affected with the long-winded Cant. howbeit, I ſhall not refuſe to commend unto you two or three very pertinent places of Scripture to the purpoſe of your expectation.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51655:18"/>
            <p>The firſt ſhall be that in <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. which contains <hi>Jothro</hi>'s Counſel unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> which ſheweth you, <hi>that you muſt endeavour to approve your ſelves able men, ſuch as fear God, men of truth, hating Covetouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ſhall be that of <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3. <hi>He that Ruleth over men muſt be Juſt, Ruling in the fear of God: Remember you bear not the Sword in vain,</hi> Rom. 13.4. The Magiſtrate is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque tabulae,</hi> the Keeper of the two Tables of the Ten Commandments: and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your Sword may not reach all cauſes; yet ſo far as lyeth in your power, let not diſorderly living paſs without ſuch puniſhments as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſtent with Chriſtian Charity.</p>
            <p>You need not that much more ſhould be ſaid by me at this inſtant; the Laws of God, and the known Laws of the Land, and the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of your own Society muſt direct you when this diſcourſe of mine may be forgotten. Let your own good example in frequenting the houſe of God, together with your own Families, according to the Order of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by Law eſtabliſht, and your own Grave, unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and diſcreet deportment, put a blank upon diſſenters. And if the Rabble will needs caſt ſcorn upon the Wiſdome of God, ſhining forth upon you in the Miniſtry of your Lawful Paſtor Ordain'd and Conſtituted amongſt you in due form and order of Law, according to the known
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51655:18"/>Laws of this Realm, and the Canons and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> piouſly and wholſomely made and provided; It is your part and duty in eſpecial manner to ſupport and countenance him againſt all affronts and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, which a factious and head-ſtrong, a Slanderous and Scandalizing Generation may caſt upon him.</p>
            <p>And for you that are <hi>ſub poteſtate Conſtituti,</hi> under the command of Authority; I ſhall give you that ſame wholſome adviſe which follows immediately after the words of my Text: <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour all men; Love the Brother-hood; Fear God, Honour the King:</hi> On which words I ſhall make no other Paraphraſe than what the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath made to my hand in her moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and plain Catechiſm. <hi>You ſhall next to the performance of your Duty towards God in believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in him, Fearing him, Loving him above all, Worſhipping him, giving him Thanks, putting your whole Truſt in him, Calling upon him, Honouring his Holy Name, and his Word, and ſerving him truly all the days of your lives.</hi> You ſhall, I ſay, next to the performance of your duty in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner towards God, <hi>not forget your duty towards your Neighbour;</hi> (that is to ſay) <hi>You ſhall love your Neighbour as your ſelf, and do unto all men, as thou would'ſt he ſhould do unto thee. Thou ſhalt Love, Honour, and Succour thy Father and Mother. Thou ſhalt Honour and Obey the King, and all that are put in Authority under him. Thou ſhalt ſubmit thy ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:51655:19"/>to all thy Governours, Teachers, Spiritual Paſtors, and Maſters. Thou ſhalt order thy ſelf Lowly and Reverently to all thy Betters. Thou ſhalt hurt no body by Word nor Deed. Thou ſhalt be True and Juſt in all thy dealings. Thou ſhalt bear no Malice nor Hatred in thy heart. Thou ſhalt keep thy Hands from picking and ſtealing, and thy Tongue from Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaking, Lying, and Slandering. Thou ſhalt keep thy Body in temperance, Soberneſs and Chaſtity. Thou ſhalt not Covet nor deſire other mens Goods; but ſhalt learn and labour truly to get thine own Living, and to do thy Duty in that ſtate of Life, unto which it hath pleaſed God to call thee.</hi> This is pure Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Undefiled before God and the Father in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. <hi>Wilt thou then not be afraid of the Power? do that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame,</hi> Rom. 13.3. For as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Who is he that will harm you, if ye be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of that which is good?</hi> I beſeech you Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what is ſpoken, and the Lord give you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all things neceſſary, in order to the Attainment of Everlaſting Salvation through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: to whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, Three Perſons, and but One God, be aſcribed and rendered, as of all due belongeth, all Honour and Glory, Praiſe, Power, Might, Majeſty, Thankſgiving, Dominion, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, both of us, and of every Creature, both now and for ever more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51655:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
